Guide to the James Braxton Craven Papers, 1961-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Braxton Craven papers 1961-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Craven, James Braxton
224.0 Linear Feet 168,210 Items
North Carolina lawyer and federal judge.
The legal and judicial papers of U.S. Circuit Court Judge James Braxton Craven span the years 1961-1977. Files of correspondence, memoranda, and legal motions and orders concern a multitude of cases in which Craven was involved. Cases include civil suits; criminal cases, including many prisoners' petitions for Writs of Habeas Corpus, particularly since Gideon v. Wainwright; and appeals from administrative boards and commissions, including the FCC, SEC, NLRB, and others. After 1970, Craven served on "three-judge" district court sessions, special courts which usually relate to civil suits raising questions of governmental policy and of constitutional law, and the files document these as well. There are also files dating from 1964-1973 which concern school integration cases. The correspondence between judges is particularly significant, revealing the intersection of personal belief and the carrying out of judicial processes in the lower and higher courts. The collection also includes a précis outlining the legal philosophy and the highlights of Craven's career, but contains very little personal material.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Braxton Craven Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1978.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1918 April 3 James Braxton Craven born in Lenoir County, N.C., son of a Methodist minister
1939 A.B., Duke University
1942 LL.B., Harvard University
1942-1946 Served in U.S. Navy
1946 Admitted to North Carolina Bar Solicitor of the Burke County Criminal Court
1948-1952 Assistant U.S. Attorney for the Western District of North Carolina
1956 Appointed North Carolina Superior Judge
1959-1960 Vice President of the North Carolina Bar Association
1961 Appointed Chief Judge of the U.S. District Court for the Western District in North Carolina
1963 Elected a member of the Institute of Judicial Administration
1966-1977 U.S. Circuit Judge, Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals
1967 Visiting professor in constitutional law at the University of North Carolina Law School
1968 Visiting professor in federal courts at the University of Texas Law School
1970 Visiting professor in constitutional law at the University of North Carolina Law School
1972-1973 Duke University Board of Trustees member
1977 May 3 Death of James Braxton Craven at age 59
Collection Overview
The legal and judicial papers of U.S. Circuit Court Judge James Braxton Craven span the years 1961-1977. Files of correspondence, memoranda, and legal motions and orders concern a multitude of cases in which Craven was involved. Cases include civil suits; criminal cases, including many prisoners' petitions for Writs of Habeas Corpus, particularly since Gideon v. Wainwright; and appeals from administrative boards and commissions, including the FCC, SEC, NLRB, and others. After 1970, Craven served on "three-judge" district court sessions, special courts which usually relate to civil suits raising questions of governmental policy and of constitutional law, and the files document these as well. There are also files dating from 1964-1973 which concern school integration cases. The correspondence between judges is particularly significant, revealing the intersection of personal belief and the carrying out of judicial processes in the lower and higher courts. The collection also includes a précis outlining the legal philosophy and the highlights of Craven's career, but contains very little personal material. Arrangement is in one large alphabetical file, prefaced by a file of biographical information.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Craven, James Braxton
Appellate courts -- North Carolina
Appellate courts -- United States
Civil rights -- Education -- United States
Courts -- United States -- History
Criminal courts -- United States
Criminal justice, Administration of -- United States
Criminal Justice Act -- United States
Federal Magistrates Act -- United States
Judges -- North Carolina
Judges -- United States -- Correspondence
Law -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Prisoners -- Legal status, laws, etc.--United States
School desegregation
North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 20th century
United States. Court of Appeals (Fourth Circuit) -- History
Contents of Collection
- Alphabetical Series, 1961-1977, (267 boxes)
  The bulk of the series is taken up by many boxes of files from U.S. Court of Appeals cases. Each box contains approximately .5 linear feet of material. Other smaller sections contain files on U.S. District Court cases, files on the Criminal Justice and the Federal Magistrates acts, correspondence between judges, school civil rights cases, administrative files, and judicial conferences.
  - Biographical information; inventory of collection (Box 1)
  - Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts: Reports, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Appellate Judges Seminar and Planning Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Appellate Justice Noational Conference, San Diego, Ca., 1975 (Box 3)
  - Clare Plan (re: standards for admission to practice in the federal courts), 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: "Crackpot Letters," 1962-1977
  - Correspondence with eleven judges, 1961-1977 (Box 5)
  - Criminal Justice Act, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Federal Magistrates Act, 1969-1970
  - School Civil Rights Cases, 1964-1973 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Court of Appeals, Fourth Circuit
    - Cases:
      - 8,790 to 15,713, 1968-1970 (Box 8-66)
      - 71-1001 to 77-1681, 1971-1977 (Box 67-222)
      - Misc. 500 to Misc. 989, 1968-1973 (Box 223-226)
      - Misc. 72-8002 to Misc. 77-8080, 1972-1977 (Box 227-239)
      - Unnumbered, 1966-1973 (Box 240)
    - Circuit Executive, 1974-1977 (Box 241-243)
    - Clerk's Office, 1974-1977 (Box 244-245)
    - Court Administration
      - Agenda and Minutes of Meetings, Judicial Council, 1968-1977 (Box 246)
      - Judicial Council Matters, 1974-1977 (Box 247-249)
    - Court Calendars and Case Notes, 1972-1977 (Box 250-251)
    - Judicial Conferences, 1970-1977 (Box 252)
    - Paper Shuffling File, 1968 (Box 253)
    - Rules, 1966-1975
  - U.S. District Court
    - Cases:
      - Maryland, 1973-1975 (Box 254)
      - N.C. Western District, 1964-1967
        - Prisoners, Habeas Corpus Cases, 1961-1966 and 1970-1971
      - N.C. Wilmington District, 1966-1977 (Box 255)
      - Pennsylvania, 1975
      - Three-Judge, 1965 and 1970-1977 (Box 256-267)